<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Sober vindication of Lt. Gen. Ludlow and others in answer to a printed letter sent from Sir Hardress Waller in Ireland, and other non-commissioned officers at Dublin to Lt. General Ludlow at Duncannon, commander in chief of all the Parliament forces in Ireland : wherein you have a faithful but summary history of the affairs in Ireland as they now stand ... / by a faithful friend to the Parliament and Commonwealth.</title>
            <author>Philanthropus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42884</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875897</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875897</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152384</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2295:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Sober vindication of Lt. Gen. Ludlow and others in answer to a printed letter sent from Sir Hardress Waller in Ireland, and other non-commissioned officers at Dublin to Lt. General Ludlow at Duncannon, commander in chief of all the Parliament forces in Ireland : wherein you have a faithful but summary history of the affairs in Ireland as they now stand ... / by a faithful friend to the Parliament and Commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>Philanthropus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 16: Philanthropus.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ludlow, Edmund, 1617?-1692.</term>
               <term>Waller, Hardress, --  Sir, 1604?-1666?</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1649-1660.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152384:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sober Vindication OF Lt. Gen. Ludlow, And others.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a <hi>Printed Letter</hi> ſent from Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and other non-commiſſioned Officers at <hi>Dublin</hi> to Lt. General <hi>Ludlow</hi> at <hi>Duncannon,</hi> Commander in chief of all the Parliaments Forces in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN You have alſo a <hi>Faithful</hi> but <hi>Summary Hiſtory</hi> of the Affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> as they now ſtand, of their <hi>Anti-Parliamentary</hi> Proceedings with the <hi>Parliaments</hi> beſt <hi>Friends,</hi> their Impriſoning and Perſecuting the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and 100. of others that ever adhered to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> indulging the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but indangering the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt, every day to the ruin of the Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a faithful Friend to the</hi> Parliament <hi>and</hi> Common-Wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpred-Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:152384:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152384:2"/>
            <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>OH Ireland! Ireland!</hi> Languiſhing under the apparent <hi>Symptoms</hi> of Death ſtruck in her very <hi>Vitalls,</hi> and ſick at her very <hi>heart!</hi> Whiles men of the moſt diſtructive <hi>Humors</hi> are the moſt predominant in that Nation! <hi>Aſpis a Vipera venum mutuatas eſt,</hi> whiles the <hi>Engliſh</hi> borrow venom of the very <hi>Iriſh,</hi> to ſting and wound our Engliſh <hi>worthies</hi> with! It is the common cry of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> real friends there! They had better looſe above half the <hi>Army</hi> then one <hi>Ludlow</hi> (leaſt they looſe all) and better halfe the <hi>Old Proteſtants</hi> and Chriſtians, then one <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, Thomlinſon</hi> or <hi>Steel;</hi> under the happineſs of whoſe <hi>healing Principles</hi> piety and <hi>Councells</hi> (as well as <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel Jones</hi> his, (a grave and gracious <hi>Senator</hi>) not ſo the <hi>Sectaries</hi> as all the <hi>Nation</hi> hath been <hi>nouriſhed</hi> and brought up very <hi>tenderly</hi> and in the very <hi>boſomes</hi> of them; therefore cannot but bemoan their danger, whiles ſome men (like <hi>Farneſe</hi> (Prince of <hi>Parma</hi>) who threatned to ſwim his horſe in the blood of the <hi>Lutherans</hi>) do boast that they will not leave <hi>one Sectary</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (that is <hi>one</hi> whom they call <hi>Sectary,</hi> which is a name they give to all godly, and the <hi>Parliaments</hi> beſt friends alike (of all judgments, <hi>Presbyterians, Independants,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi>) and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at this day, as there be many <hi>Families</hi> removing to come away, ſo it is thought above <hi>500 Families</hi> of the beſt <hi>Engliſh</hi> in all <hi>Ireland</hi> will be <hi>ſhortly</hi> over, if not timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived; (kept and incouraged in their <hi>callings</hi> and <hi>plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> during their pious and <hi>peaceable</hi> deportment.) Wherefore O Lord! If <hi>Ireland</hi> yet may live! Make our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament wiſe! Our <hi>Phiſitians</hi> able and skilfull to <hi>recover</hi> her! Seeing <hi>non licet bis errare,</hi> one errour in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now, will abſolutely <hi>ruine</hi> all their intereſts there as well as <hi>ours;</hi> and is more <hi>then</hi> a <hi>100 errours</hi> in former times, if not irrecoverable.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152384:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152384:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F all men were wiſe, I have ſaid enough, for perſons that were moſt of them reducible for their former actings in the late Apoſtacy, from the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of a Common-wealth, upon groundleſs jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies and ſleight ſuſpitions; To throw off their Noble General under the Parliament, is doubtleſs an Action unwarrantable, unjuſtifiable, and vituperable, and there can be no better intention in it then the Jews had in crucifying of our Lord Jeſus, for Mother-wit will tell every man, that they ought to have obeyed him, until the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had ſignified their pleaſure to the contrary, and that it is a frivolous allegation to ſay, <hi>That they will obey him upon ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Parliaments pleaſure,</hi> for, his Commiſſion gives him Poſſeſſion till it be ſuperceded, otherwiſe Servants may turn out their Maſters, and ſay, <hi>That upon order from the Juſtices they will reſtore his Poſſeſſion;</hi> And as it is a dreadful preſident, ſo it is a pretty invention of the firſt impreſſion (never any brave Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander being ſo unhanſomly ſerved before) thereby to blaſt any mans reputation upon a bare ſuſpition, as the Polititian adviſes, boldly to callumniate, that ſomething may be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, though this worthy Patriot be like pure Marble that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can ſtick upon him, but the generallity being apt to contract Matrimony with the firſt Narrative, if it be my duty to relieve my Neighbours Ox when fallen, much more am I obliged in the abſence of this worthy Perſon as a friend to the publick, he having been ſo cordial a friend to all honeſt men, and one whom I have for many yeares honoured for his Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues (or rather the gifts and graces of God in him) he not having the benefit of a Preſſe to vindicate him (if there were any need of it) leaſt ſilence ſhould give ſome credit to that which in it ſelfe hath not the weight of a Pin in the Ballance of right Reaſon, I am preſt in my Spirit (though unknowing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, ſo far as the notorietie of the Fact will comport to give it a ſudden anſwer, according to the beſt information I could get by letter and relation. The materials in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſponſible are,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152384:4"/>1. That whereas Lt. Generall <hi>Ludlow</hi> writ to Lt. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Puckle</hi> Governour of <hi>Roſse</hi> to preſerve his Garriſon for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> they ſay he had done it before he had any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from him, this is a miſtake, for Lt. Generall <hi>Ludlow</hi> left Lt. Colonell <hi>Puckle</hi> in poſſeſſion for the Parliament, whereof he was never diſpoſſeſt to this hour.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For what concernes Colonel <hi>Jones</hi> actings, I intend not to intermeddle, he has been a wiſe Counſellour, a faithfull man, and one that feared God above many, true to a Common-Wealths Principles in times of temptation, and therefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumably he has not declined when there was not the leaſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to decline Parliamentary Authority in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. They proceed to doubtings, and to ſtrong ſuſpitions that Lt. Generall <hi>Ludlow</hi> hath not been a friend to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that is, hath not been a friend to himſelfe, no man can ſecure himſelfe from ſuſpition, from guilt he may; I do not in the leaſt intend to beſpatter the ſubſcribers, but to wipe off that dirt which they would caſt upon the face of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Patriot, onely preſumtive Objections may be ſatisfied by preſumptive Anſwers; I believe that neither he nor they have intended to ſet up for themſelves, ſo as to diſown the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, but if ſuſpition ſhould ſtand for any proof, let but the perſons, their principles, former practiſes and actings, be ponderated, if ſufferance for the party beloved in Perſon &amp; Eſtate, if declining and refuſing to act under the ſingle perſon, when others upon their earneſt ſeekings had warm imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under him, be the beſt Arguments of Fidelity to the Parliament; Let the Impartial Reader judge, whether Lt. G. <hi>Ludlow</hi> or his Antagoniſts have manifeſted moſt conſtant, good affection to their juſt Authority; and for modern ſuſpition, what mean the Letters from <hi>Doublin,</hi> that many of the Officers there will have a Free Parliament? what means the impriſonment of the Parliaments conſtant Servants and Champions, <hi>Jones, Tom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linſon, Pretty, Wallis, Abbot, Brafield, Jones, Smith, Bennet, Lowe, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon, Roberts</hi> and others, many whereof declared with the firſt, and yet might not be truſted with their commands? What means the ſelf conferring of two Regiments upon Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller,</hi> two upon Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> and three upon his brothers? ſo as upon the matter, two men have ſeven Regiments. What
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152384:4"/>
means the diſarming of the Anabaptiſts, and the Parliaments beſt friends, that they muſt not wear a Sword, ſaying they are Sectarians, and not fit to be truſted? And how do they prove one to be an Anabaptiſt or Sectarian? but becauſe he prayes in his Family, or ſuch a one prayes by the Spirit; What means the Liſting &amp; taking in of Cavileers, Perſons diſaffected to the Parliament, and any that will but revile the Sectariſts? but onely to model and put the Army in ſuch a poſture and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to be in a prepared readineſſe to receive <hi>Charles Stuart</hi> at a weeks warning, though that muſt not be yet mentioned, the deſign muſt be firſt to bring in the Excluded Members in 1648. and then comes in ding dong bells, King, Lords and Commons: It would be leſs danger to call in the <hi>Spaniard, Turk,</hi> or the great <hi>Mogul.</hi> What means the impriſonment of Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> at his landing, ſent thither to preach by Order from the Parliament? O <hi>Dublin, Dublin, Thou that killeſt the Prophets, and ſtoneſt or impriſoneſt them which are ſent unto thee,</hi> as that worthy Servant of Chriſt, who was caſt into the Common Priſon, wit out admitting him <hi>Bayl,</hi> or a <hi>hearing,</hi> with a high affront to the <hi>Parliaments Authority</hi> ſo unhumanely handled, and yet he is no <hi>Anabaptiſt;</hi> So that worthy Miniſter Mr. <hi>Enoch Grey</hi> being ſhut out by the Pariſh from Preaching, dare not ſtir abroad, being threatned by the Porters and Watermen to be ſtoned or thrown into the Water, and yet he is no <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt:</hi> The like to Mr. <hi>Wotten</hi> another godly <hi>Miniſter,</hi> kept out of his Pulpit, confined to his own houſe, and yet no <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt;</hi> Beſides ſuch uſage of the <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Parliaments</hi> choiſeſt Friends, who are far from being <hi>Factious,</hi> or giving the leaſt occaſion to ſuch cruelty. O what! What means the Parliament-like Convention to meet at <hi>Dublin</hi> the 24 of <hi>January,</hi> with other diſmal news from thence? as if the Intereſt of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Good Old Cauſe of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Righteouſneſs, were taking leave of poor <hi>Ireland!</hi> Yea, What means the <hi>Arming</hi> ſo many <hi>ill affected</hi> perſons! the diſarming and plundering the <hi>Parliaments</hi> beſt friends and <hi>well affected</hi> (that are no <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> neither;) The impowering of the Native <hi>Iriſh</hi> (as the <hi>Mayor</hi> of <hi>Dublin</hi> is for one) with the Sword! And the caſting out the moſt Noble <hi>Engliſh,</hi> expoſing them as ſo many <hi>naked perſons</hi> to the moſt barbarous rage and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152384:5"/>
revenge of their Enemies! with a 1000 more ſuch ſad ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Parliaments Intereſt,</hi> groveling on the <hi>Ground,</hi> and <hi>gaſping</hi> for life in that <hi>Lamentable Nation!</hi> But they will ſay, that the ſtrongeſt preſumptions will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the weakeſt proof, though ſomething may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, if others ſhould deal with them as they have dealt with pretious <hi>Ludlow;</hi> for they made ſuſpition the only ground of his non-admiſſion and rejection, by a learned Vote of the Stratagem-makers and Surpriſers of <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle (when every ſoul within it, was for the Parliament, for ought I ever heard to the contrary) that Lt. G. <hi>Ludlow</hi> had given ſuſpition, to be no friend to the Parliament, and therefore ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the head of the Army, when but very few dayes before by their Declaration <hi>December,</hi> 14. they had owned him for their lawful ſuperior.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But they confeſs they are ſo bold as to open his letters, wherein they miſtake one letter; for they would make that to be High Treaſon, which no doubt if it be well conſidered is pure reaſon, it is obſerved by a Learned Miniſter that ſnaching at Scripture, not wel weighing the Antecedent and Conſequent, is the ground of many Hereſies. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. Was miſalleadged, to keep thee in all thy ways, omitted. One ſaid that Jeſus Chriſt was an Antinomian becauſe he ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.40. <hi>hang all the Law and the Prophets,</hi> leaving out, <hi>on theſe two Commandments,</hi> who knowes what dependance or coherence the words charged have upon other parts of the Letter which are theſe, we ſeem to be neceſſitated to look towards the Old Parliament, tis to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they will be very high in caſe they ſhould be brought in without conditions, probably he expreſt other mens opinions and feares rather then his own, and that the words immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately preceding were, that it is the opinion of moſt, that we ſeem. &amp;c. But take them as ſubſtantives, their genuine and candid conſtruction will ſoon appear.</p>
            <p>They Object, <hi>That Lt. G.</hi> Ludlow, <hi>hearing of the force put upon the Parliament, at</hi> Conway, <hi>inſtead of returning back to his Command,</hi> wrote only a Letter to Colonel <hi>Jones, importing that he had received a letter from a factious party, that a ſtop for that preſent was put upon the Parliaments ſitting, and a door of hope opened to bring them to their duty:</hi> It is ſome ingenuity they will confeſſe,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152384:5"/>
ſo much of Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> and ſome other of the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents, with whom Lt. G. L. held correſpondence, would pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh what they know concerning his great diſſatisfactions and abominating of the Anti-Parliamentary tranſaction during their interruptions, which by virtue of the ninth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement they are obliged to do.</p>
            <p>Speak out Gentle-men, you cannot equivocate with the Lord, his faithfulneſs to the Parliament would be as evident as <hi>Abrahams</hi> Servant was to his Maſter; Doth it not argue ſome deteſtation of the force, to ſay, <hi>it was done by a Factious Partie?</hi> And when he firſt heard of it at <hi>Bewmoris,</hi> ſome credible perſons that were with him ſay, that he took on extreamly, lookt paler upon it then ever he did when he met with an enemy, that it was Dagger news unto him; and at <hi>Cheſter,</hi> when ſome deſired him to put a favourable conſtruction upon it, as if there were ſome neceſſity for it, he ſaid, <hi>It was a neceſſity of the Devils ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and that there was no viſible means under Heaven to ſave the Nations, but by a ſudden reſtitution of the Parliament,</hi> or words to that effect; if then Lt. G.L. having experimented the force of Eloquence and perſwaſion to be great in bringing about the happy Reſtauration of the ſixth of <hi>May,</hi> he Repaired to <hi>London</hi> to be inſtrumental in another incruental Revolution, as ſome worthy Patriots call it, not doubting but that he had left <hi>Ireland</hi> in ſafe and truſty hands for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and might be more uſeful by dealing with the underſtandings of the Interrupters; what better ſervice could he do for the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary</hi> Intereſt? The noble General at <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and General <hi>Monk</hi> have done worthily and moſt honourably like true Common-wealths men, their Names ſhall be immortal, and I wiſh them golden Statues; but that derrogates nothing from the Wiſdom, Valour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Honour of the noble Lt. G. L. The <hi>Parliaments</hi> Forces have alwayes done as much (<hi>precando,</hi> as <hi>praeliando</hi>) by praying as by fighting, God is the Creator of this <hi>Parliaments</hi> Re-introduction and Re-inveſtiture; but he has had his Oratours to plead for it with himſelf, and thoſe who oppoſed it: The Sword abroad doth beſt when there is good Counſel at home; I ſay, if Lt. G.L. or any other worthy Patriot did elect to ſuſtain the perſon of a Mediator, Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Advocate, <hi>Orator hoſtia aut internuncius,</hi> to Reconcile
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152384:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152384:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152384:7"/>
and make up that unhappy Breach, to compoſe the difference without blood: So as with <hi>Joſhua</hi> to make the <hi>Achanns</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their guilt, to plead the Law for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereof he is a Member, to mind them of their Covenants and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Engagements to be faithful to the beſt Maſters that ever Souldiers had (not as perſons Mercenary, but honourary ſo long as they are true to the <hi>Parliamentary</hi> truſt) to entreat them by their Tergiverſations not to open a door to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, to be a faithful <hi>Referendary</hi> or Meſſenger to other worthy Members of <hi>Parliament</hi> how to ſteer for beſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick advantage; and to be as a ſacrifice to expoſe his perſon to hazard, if they ſhould not hearken to ſound Advice, as well for their own good, as for the good of the Nations; and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly if he did inculcate and preſs it upon them, that if they did ſpontaneouſly and ſuddenly remove the force, and take off the interruption of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> poſſibly they might have good Conditions, an Act of Indempnity, as much as ever could be expected; but if the <hi>Parliament</hi> were brought in by Force, they muſt expect to loſe all that was dear unto them, telling them that by the ſeries of Providence they ſeem neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated ſo to do; and if thereupon Lt. G. L. did write to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Jones</hi> in thoſe Expreſſions, what moderate judicious man can make any more of it, but that he had great hopes of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Return, and was much afraid that the Officers at <hi>Wallingford</hi> Houſe ſhould perſiſt in their defection and revolt, until the <hi>Parliament</hi> would ſhew them no mercy; for what could be intended by other Conditions, but an Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity; and what honeſt man would not have been grieved to the heart to ſee the great Officers, <hi>Fleetwood, Lambert,</hi> and others, that had been ſo eminently inſtrumental in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the powers of the common Enemy after all their good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices to have become themſelves objects of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere ſtroak of Juſtice, who ſince (bleſſed be God) have taſted of their Mercy by another happy Act of Indempnity, whereby the <hi>Parliament</hi> have gained more Honour then by all their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Victories; and I am confident have more firmly engaged the hearts of all good men to live and die with them, then any tongue can expreſs: <hi>Caeſar dando ignoſcendo adeptus eſt gloriam;</hi> when <hi>Parliaments</hi> are ſo juſtly offended, they are both parties
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152384:7"/>
and Judges, and it is moſt Heroical to condonate what is done againſt ones ſelf, it ſhews that there is not one drop of revenge lodging in their noble breaſts; and for this Act of Oblivion of ſo great a prevarication, having forgiven the like offence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, our noble Senators ſhall be had in glorious and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrance, <hi>Arbor honoretur cujus nos umbra tuetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Exception taken to the Letter, is to the title of <hi>Dear Friend</hi> given to Colonel <hi>Jones;</hi> but this is an Obſervation againſt the Laws of Friendſhip and Humanity, as if it came rather from a <hi>Quaker</hi> then from perſons of ſuch Quality: our Lord Chriſt ſaid to the man that wanted his wedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou in hither?</hi> And <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dives, Son, remember;</hi> Shall we argue from thence that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was guilty of <hi>Dives</hi> covetouſneſs; and the Epithete <hi>Dear,</hi> is but <hi>(pro more loci)</hi> the Cuſtome of the Nation, not one <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhman</hi> of an hundred that uſeth any other compellation then <hi>Loving Friend,</hi> or <hi>Dear Friend;</hi> but how can theſe Gentlemen anſwer it, that in the beginning of their Letter ſay Lt. <hi>General</hi> Ludlow <hi>ſtands accuſed of High Treaſon;</hi> and in the cloſe of it ſay, <hi>We remain your humble Servants?</hi> Doth this argue their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Treaſon if there were any? It is well known here, and ſome of them cannot be ignorant of it, that as ſoon as L. G. L. heard of any ſuch intended Subſcription, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared his abhorring thereof, and juſt indignation againſt ſuch as had a hand in it; and immediately, as he ſaid, ſent away Letters into <hi>Ireland</hi> to Colonel <hi>Jones,</hi> and others, ſome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have ſeen to this effect; in general, admiring and bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the unfaithfulneſſe of men; and particularly, had the Subſcribers amongſt you, or rather thoſe that prompted thoſe Subſcriptions, contrived a way to render themſelves obnoxious to the reproaches of thoſe who watch to blaſt even Religion it ſelf, for the ſake of thoſe who profeſs it, I know not how they could have met with a more ready one then this, when there was not the leaſt temptation for them after a ſolemne Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the contrary, to eſpouſe a perſonal. Intereſt, having been ſo lately betrayed by the like Confidence, and to do it in ſo under-hand a way, when all the Officers, who (when they were altogether declared againſt it) were gone to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Charges; &amp; this to the trampling under foot, the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152384:8"/>
Authority by whom they were intruſted &amp; Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated: For my part I can as little ſee the prudence of it as the honeſty; for they have thereby, in the Judgement of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different perſons ſacrificed their prudence, honour, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; And if in that Letter to Colonel <hi>Jones</hi> he mentioned any thing, of his fearing the Reſtoring of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> it was but <hi>(ſperare pro timere)</hi> Fear put for Hope; for I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there are above twenty Letters extant in <hi>Ireland,</hi> wherein he expreſſed his great Hopes of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Re-ſitting, as I have often heard him moſt affectionately ſay, That <hi>this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are the only leaves of the tree of life, which (under God) muſt be for the healing of the Nations; they are the only ligitimate ſpouſe, all other Conventions are but as Concubines, becauſe no power upon earth can le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally ſummon a Parliament, nor any but this Parliament, ſave theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from ruine and confuſion;</hi> with many ſuch like paſſionate Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, arguing a reſtleſneſs and total diſſatisfaction till this happy <hi>Parliament,</hi> the joy of Saints, and honour of Jeſus Chriſt, were reſtored.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is further obſerved that in the ſame Letter he writes, <hi>I hope er'e this the Commiſſions for ſetting Civil Juſtice on the wheels in</hi> Ireland <hi>are come unto your hands, which were ſent by the power of thoſe who had violated the Parliaments Authority:</hi> Theſe Objectors had either bad intelligence, or bad memories; for ſo ſoon as the Names of thoſe Commiſſioners were ſent from <hi>Ireland</hi> they were approved of; And in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt there was an Order of <hi>Parliament</hi> for the Holding of Aſſizes in <hi>Ireland</hi> by reaſon of the great want of Juſtice there; which Order being of force at the time of the unhappy interruption, whether it might not be as well obſerved for the Advancement of Juſtice as well as the Exciſe and Cuſtoms, are received in <hi>Ireland</hi> for ſome time by virtue of <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Order, is not for me to determine; however the Commiſſioners therein named, as I underſtand, did not think fit to act thereupon.</p>
            <p>But there are Two Things whereof I perceive theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ignorant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They argue as if <hi>Lt. G.L.</hi> had been one of the confederates at <hi>Wallingford</hi> houſe againſt the Parliament, whereas it is well known in <hi>London,</hi> that though he was named by the Army to be of the Committee of Safety, and for nomination ſo called,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152384:8"/>
he utterly refuſed to act in either; or in any ſort to own them or to make any Application to them as in any Civil ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, reſolving to continue faithful to the Parliament, and endeavouring to the moſt what in him lay that they might return to the exerciſe of their juſt Authority without blood.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are not willing to underſtand what great &amp; faithful ſervice Lt G. L. and others performed at their meeting with the Officers at <hi>Wallingford</hi> houſe, by breaking and diſturbing their Councells and Reſolutious, making them like <hi>Penelopes</hi> Webb, reſolving and altering, ſhewing them the errour and vanity of all that they did, that they were like men build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Sand, that there was no firm Rock or foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to build upon, no Power to maintain the Laws, and ſecure the Rights and Liberties of the People, but onely this Renowned Parliament, and when contrary to Reaſon they had reſolved ſomething about conſervators, (<hi>viz.</hi> viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or prevaricators) Senate and Parliament, it is well known that Lt. G. L. the next day made his Proteſtation againſt it, and ſaid they would be neceſſitated to reſtore the Parliament, and the ſooner they did it the better it would be for them, and not knowing what condition <hi>Ireland</hi> might be in, whether in Peace or blood, haſted thither ſo ſoon as poſſibly he could, Being adviſed ſo to do by ſome of the Honourable Members of Parliament, I confeſſe if it had ſo pleaſed God that he had not left <hi>Ireland,</hi> or had returned a Moneth ſooner, or might ſuddenly return, with others of his like, faithful and tender ſpirits, impowred, and all due incouragement to the Officers there, ſo far as they have owned and affected the Parliaments Intereſt, <hi>Ireland</hi> may get to live, to ſee happy dayes, and honeſt People have quiet habitations there; but if a ſpirit of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and aſperitie ſhall Predominate and be uppermoſt, they muſt return for <hi>England,</hi> ſuch as know how to live here, or it would be a great favour if the Parliament would lend the poor Sectarians of that Nation, ſhipping to tranſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into <hi>America,</hi> to work there for their living, and to pray for the proſperity of the Parliament and this Common-wealth; but the reaſon of his going for <hi>Ireland,</hi> was not from any grain of fear that he had of the Parliaments diſpleaſure,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152384:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152384:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152384:10"/>
but upon the importunity of many good People from <hi>Ireland,</hi> who were full of fears and jealouſies, impatiently intreating and beſeeching him to haſt away, not knowing what the danger of a few dayes delay might be, for whoſe ſake he made ſuch expedition, thinking to have been the more welcome there for bringing ſo good news, as the re-ſitting of the Parliament, but was rejected at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and ſo went to <hi>Duncannon,</hi> which by the objectors favour, was a better courſe then to have returned at their Command, for not being conſcious to himſelf of the leaſt unfaithfulneſs to the Parliament, he had no reaſon to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the legality or validity of his Commiſſion, being as good as ever it was, and how any Soldiers durſt in ſo preſumptuous a manner, upon ſuch ſlender and trivial ſuſpitions, draw their ſwords againſt their lawful General, whether they ought not to have received him, &amp; then to have humbly remonſtrated to the Parliament what they had againſt him, or whether they did well to be their own Judges to condemn him unheard, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him as an enemy, is humbly ſubmitted to the Parliaments great wiſdom, ſo that upon the whole matter I do not find all that is charged upon this worthy Perſon to be of ſo much weight, as the Feather that was in ſome bodies Cap in <hi>Dublin</hi> fields at the late Muſter, when the People made acclamations, for joy, that there ſhould not be an <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> nor a Sectariſt left in <hi>Ireland.</hi> I have but three words to add.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That this tranſaction againſt Lt. G.L. hath been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced proſecuted, and the wheels drawn, by four unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Steeds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Falſitie.</hi> And 1. They gave it out to win the Souldiers, that Lt. G.L. had ſent letters over to ſome of them to ſecure <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle, and to impriſon the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> therein, for that the ſaid <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> and Sectarians had reſolved to cut many of the old Proteſtants throats and to impriſon the reſt of them in the ſaid Caſtle, and that the time was agreed upon when it ſhould be done. 2. They told the Souldiers they had fix Moneths pay ready for them if they would caſt off their Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Officers and take others, from them. 3. Within two or three dayes after the ſurprize of the Caſtle, it was reported that they had found great ſtore of Armes and Ammunition in the houſes of ſome of the Sectarians, which they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152384:10"/>
for the purpoſe aforeſaid, which were but a Birding piece, an old <hi>Piſtol,</hi> or ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> There being ſome heart-burnings, animoſities &amp; Jealouſies about difference in opinions, ſome of the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors at <hi>Dublin</hi> (who judge, that union with the head, ought to be the ground of all Chriſtian Communion between the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) appointed a meeting for the propagation of brotherly love and affection, wherein ſome refuſed to joyn, becauſe <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> frequented the meeting; but ſo ſoon as the plot was laid for ſurprizing <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle, ſome of thoſe refuſers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired a conference in order to a Reconciliation, where Col. <hi>Tomlinſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Winter,</hi> Juſtice <hi>Cooke,</hi> Col. <hi>Laurence,</hi> Lt. Colonel <hi>Jones</hi> Governour of the Caſtle, Major <hi>Warren,</hi> and others, were appointed to be preſent, when all perſons being ſecure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent upon it, the Tueſday before the meeting, the Caſtle was ſurprized, the Sectarians all diſarmed, Bone-fires made, and other great ſolemnities, for joy that no Sectarian ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Army, and healths drunk to their confuſion, Mr. <hi>Madder</hi> diſcountenanced and diſcouraged, news brought to Mr. <hi>Blackwood</hi> that if he Preacht any more at <hi>Chicheſter</hi> houſe, his throat ſhould be cut, which Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> hearing of, gave ſtrict order that no violence ſhould be done unto him, Doctor <hi>Harding</hi> and his friends driven from their meeting place, and all this pretended for the ſervice of the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Treachery.</hi> For, ſo ſoon as notice was given that <hi>Dublin</hi> Caſtle was taken, they ſent to other gariſons for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence therein, who very chearfully and unanminouſly all the Nation over declared for the Parliament, but deſired that all might reſt in peace and quiet till they could hear from them or Lt. G. L. but within few dayes after, they Voted his non-admiſſion, in caſe he ſhould attempt to come over, as ſuſpecting him to be no friend to the Parliament, and gave it out that the Gariſons could not be ſafe in the hands of Sectaries or ſuch as favoured them, which ſo ſudden a receſſion from their Declaration for the Parliament, wherein they had owned Lt. G. L. as Commander in chief, put ſome of the Commiſſioned Officers to a demurre, as <hi>Pretty, Phare, Wallis, Abbot, Brayfield, Smith, Bennet, Denniſon</hi> and others who cheerfully declared for the Parliament, but were not free to leave their Commands or to receive orders from any
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152384:11"/>
but from their lawful ſuperiors, whereupon Sir <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> wrote letters to diveres of them, deſiring their ſpeedy repair to <hi>Dublin</hi> for further ſatisfaction, promiſing them all Freedom &amp; Civil uſage, where they were no ſooner arrived, but inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guards were ſet upon them, or were clapt in priſon; ſoon after was ſent over, the Act of Indempnity, which inſtead of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obediencee to it, they hurried away their priſoners to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Caſtles, having impriſoned ſuch as never ſubſcribed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the letter to General <hi>Munck,</hi> or the Ingagement for a General, or in the leaſt acted againſt the Parliament, (and as I have been told, ſome of them, put in Irons,) and as the laſt letters from <hi>Ireland</hi> import, they are ſtill taking up and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning honeſt men dayly, as if the Act of Indemnity did not extend to <hi>Ireland,</hi> hoping all ſhall be approved of, that they do, which if I know any thing in the world they have need of an Act of Indemnity themſelves; how unlike is this to Gallant General <hi>Munck</hi> who never impriſoned one man that promiſed to fight for the Parliament, and of the many hundreds which I hear are impriſoned in <hi>Ireland,</hi> there is not one of them, but promiſed, to be faithful to the Parliament againſt all oppoſers, and being told that they were Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and not to be truſted, they proffered their Paroles to be quiet, or to give good ſecurity to attend the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments pleaſure, yet nothing would ſerve but violence and diſgrace to their perſons; but the beſt jeſt is, that having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carcerated whom they pleaſe, and diſpoſed of, and given away their Commands and Places to others, they have publiſhed a Declaration, that notwithſtanding, before the firſt of March, any of them ſo caſheered, may have a Tryal at a Court Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal for their Places; I never thought that any, pretending to be Judges for the Parliament, would firſt have Condemned and Executed any man, and after take Adviſe whether Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy be allowable in the Caſe: <hi>(quo te ambitio trahit)</hi> but who muſt be their Judges of the Court Marſhal? not the Perſon whoſe Command is in queſtion, but thoſe whoſe Title is no better, being both Parties and Judges, and ſo claw me and I'le claw thee.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Cruelty,</hi> when L. G. <hi>Ludlow</hi> came to an Anchor in the Bay of <hi>Dublin,</hi> he ſent a Letter by Mr. <hi>Alder,</hi> to theſe Officers at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152384:11"/>
               <hi>Dublin</hi> to give them notice of it, intending to have landed early the next morning, but Sr. <hi>Hardreſs Waller</hi> upon receit of the Letter, commits Mr. <hi>Alder</hi> into the Sheriffs houſe, keeps two of the Sea-men Priſoners, and ſent a party of Horſe to hinder his landing, who thereupon deſired a right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding between them, and that he might have ſome Proviſion ſent by his ſervant, a Ship-board, which was refuſed, and not a bit of Bread or drop of freſh Water after the firſt day, might be ſent to him by any upon pain of impriſonment, and the high diſpleaſure of the Officers at <hi>Dublin;</hi> L. G. L. notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (having waited their pleaſure three or four dayes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours being uſed to make a Muttering among the Sea-men, &amp; to fire the Frigot <hi>with Granado's,</hi> as is reported) ſet Sail from thence to <hi>Duncannon,</hi> where he was received at the fort, but was not permitted to have any Proviſions from <hi>Waterford</hi> for his moneys, for himſelf or the Sea-men, though he had payed for 1500 weight of Bisket, it was forcibly taken away and the Country People frighted, and forced to drive away their Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel from about <hi>Duncannon,</hi> being told by the Souldiers that L. G. L. was a Traytor, and run away from the Parliament, with adulatory and minatory meſſages ſent into the Fort, that if the Souldiers would throw their General over the Walls, they ſhould be made Officers and have their Arrears; if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, they ſhould be ſent to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and ſerve ſeven years Apprentiſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2ly, It is very neceſſary to conſider the riſe of theſe ſtrange Tranſactions, ſo far as any thing was really intended for the Parliaments ſervice it is highly to be honoured and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, I hope all honeſt men will acquieſce and rejoyce in it; but L. G. L. and the Army in <hi>Ireland</hi> were generally for the Parliament, without any heſitation or warping; and thus it was, L. G. L. at his being in <hi>Ireland,</hi> made it his buſineſs to diſcriminate and diſtinguiſh ſuch Officers of the Army as had in any meaſure born their Teſtimony againſt the late A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy, and that were faithful to the Parliamentary Intereſt; from ſuch as had not been ſo cordial, &amp; there was a liſt agreed upon to be preſented to the Parliament; thoſe that were omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted being left in the heads of their Commands, fearing a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement, began to conſult how to continue in their Places;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152384:12"/>
in that interim the Officers of the Army from <hi>London</hi> ſent over an Engagement in Lt. G. <hi>Ludlows</hi> Abſence, to ſet up a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in oppoſition to the Parliament, which abominable thing was not ſo zealouſly proteſted againſt as it ſhould have been, but in order to keep the Peace of the Nation, with a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention as was pretended, too many ſubſcribed it, who had alſo ſome of them ſent a diſcouraging Letter to Renowned General <hi>Monk,</hi> hereupon the children of this world being wiſer in their generation then the Children of Light, that which the Commiſſioned Officers ſhould have done, namely, to have fully declared for the Parliament againſt the factious Party in <hi>England</hi> who oppoſed them, the Non-commiſſioned Officers did, ingroſſing all the applauſe and glory of it to ſuch as probably had otherwiſe been reduced, refuſing the aſſiſtance of any that had Commiſſions from the Parliament, fearing there might not be honour enough for them all; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the falacy! for as I have credibly heard many, and ſome of thoſe who are now impriſoned, were then draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a Declaration for the Parliament, to be ſent to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers at <hi>Wallingford</hi>-houſe, which theſe Gentlemen hearing of, made the more haſte to prevent them; But bleſſed be God that it is done, if the Cauſe of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs may proceed and proſper, I hope the Sectarians will rejoyce whatever becomes of them. All this was done by the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and incitement of ſuch of the Clergy, as are implacable enemies to the Sectarians, and the true Reaſon of this diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and oppoſition, why they are ſo angry with L. G. L. is, becauſe they think he too much favours the Sectarians, though like a prudent Father, he manifeſts an equal affection to all honeſt men of different apprehenſions, and being one who I am confident was never angry with any man for being no wiſer then God had made him, but his delight is in the Saints, and in ſuch as excel in virtue; and it being obſerved that the Sectarian Officers, ſo called, keep a more vigilant eye, and hold a ſtricter hand upon the Souldiers, then others did, puniſhing them for ſwearing, drunkenneſs, abſence from Gods ſervice, or their duty, and the leaſt diſorders and unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the Souldiers hoping for and being promiſed more freedom and liberty under other Commanders, were willing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152384:12"/>
to ſhake off the yoak, and ſold their Officers, ſome upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of their Arrears, ſome for a Barrel of Beer, and others for Trifles: So as in effect the Victory ſo much boaſted of in <hi>Ireland</hi> is only over the poor <hi>Sectarians,</hi> who are cordial Friends and Servants to this Parliament.</p>
            <p>My Prayers are that God would make this Parliament wiſe as Angels of light, to diſcover the depth of this profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, a greater Riddle, then when it was for the King and Parliament, againſt the King, for here all Perſons are for the Parliament, L. G. L. the lawful Commander under the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet all Perſons that went to ſee him muſt be clapt up, and all that were ſuſpected to be for him, uſed like Traytors, (and himſelf worſe, not being allowed a bit of Bread) for if any one ſpake for an honeſt man at <hi>Dublin,</hi> that bond might be taken for his appearance, the Officers and Souldiers know the Law ſo well, that they ſay, it is High Treaſon, and no Bail muſt be taken for him; and ſome of the Lawyers in <hi>Dublin</hi> are ſo learned, that they ſay, that notwithſtanding the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, they may keep any man in Priſon whom they ſuſpect.</p>
            <p>Thirdly &amp; Laſtly, I wiſh it may be ſeriouſly conſidered, that though the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Independents</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> have been pecking one at another, yet the true ground of the Conteſt, is not between them, but betwixt the Common Enemy and them, the Prelatical, Epiſcopal Common-prayer-book Party (which are the moſt numerous) will gladly joyn with the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> to cruſh and trample upon the <hi>Independents;</hi> but that being done, they muſt fall upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> for they hate the very Name of Paſtors, Teachers, Elders or Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, they muſt have Biſhops, Parſons, and Church-wardens, and ſuch poor Over-ſeers as formerly they had, they will not endure to be Examined or to give any Reaſon of their Faith before they come to the Sacrament, they will not endure any Miniſter that ſhall endeavour to make a ſeparation between the precious and the vile, onely the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſhall be reſerved for the laſt morſel, as <hi>Polyphemus</hi> ſaid of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes;</hi> And as ſome of them ſaid of an honeſt <hi>Alderman</hi> of that <hi>City,</hi> that this is all the favour he ſhould have, to be one of the <hi>laſt</hi> that ſhould be baniſhed the <hi>City;</hi> And as they have already ſhut the door againſt Mr. <hi>Wells</hi> at <hi>Cork,</hi> Mr. <hi>Grey,</hi> Mr.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152384:13"/>
               <hi>Wootton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſpinal</hi> which are no <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> but able and godly Miniſters of the New Teſtament, ſo it is reported that they have turned out Mr. <hi>Gilbert,</hi> and are putting out Mr. <hi>Chambers,</hi> and then one or two more ſtars being ſet, Dr. <hi>Winter</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baynes,</hi> the light of the Goſpel will be extinct at <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blin,</hi> and what remains but groſs <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkneſs? If theſe powers at <hi>Dublin</hi> be ſuch real friends to the Parliament, why are theſe things ſuffered, that any godly Miniſter or other Perſons, who are the faithfulleſt friends of the Parliament there ſhould be turned out of their Places and Imployments, either of the Military or Civil liſt? and many of them I hear which brought Horſes to mount themſelves caſheered without any Pay, and expoſed to a begging or ſtarving condition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of an Order from Sr. <hi>Hardreſs Waller,</hi> that none who were liſted by <hi>L. G. L.</hi> ſhall receive any Pay as the reſt of the Souldiers until further Order; theſe are High Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which I truſt the Parliament will never give them any thanks for, being as unlike to Parliamentary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings as light to darkneſs.</p>
            <p>They conclude with a ſuppoſition that if Lt. G. L's. actings, have not incapacited him to ſit in Parliament, and I ſay if their actings have not merited to be left liable to a multitude of actions of Treſpaſs and battery and falſe impriſonment, it is well for them; for it is not enough to do (<hi>bonum</hi> but <hi>bene</hi>) a good thing but by lawful meanes, and I find it now the Cave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers maſter-peece (yea there) to aſperſe the precious Members o Parliament calling them the <hi>Rump,</hi> and crying up a <hi>Free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> there being ſo very few that are faithful to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth (we had need be the more earneſt in praying and acting for them) hoping thereby to bring in <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> but I truſt they are ſo wiſe as to obſerve theſe things, and that Gods Bleſſing and Preſence ſhall continue among them by the Multiplication of all his Benedictions and Graces upon them and theirs, I onely crave leave to conceal my Name and to ſubſcribe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>PHILANTHROP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, a great ſinner, but faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Parliament, and one that loves the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth as his own life.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
